UMASS-Amherst Women's Studies Department Collection, 1960-1986
Sophia Smith Collection
UMASS-Amherst Women's Studies Department Collection
1960-1986
University of Massachusetts (Amherst campus). Dept. of Women's Studies
MS 350
3 boxes (3.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Resource files from the UMASS-Amherst Women's Studies Department containing printed material on a variety of topics relating to women including abortion, rape, lesbianism, domestic violence, reproductive rights, journalism, literature, the arts, prostitution and women's rights.
Historical Note
The Women's Studies Department at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst was begun in 1974. It is one of the oldest and largest programs of its kind in the United States. Its objective is to introduce students to analytical tools and basic approaches to the study of women in a variety of fields.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The UMASS-Amherst Women's Studies Department is the source of this collection rather than its substance. These are resource files from the Women's Studies Department containing printed material on a variety of topics relating to women including abortion, rape, lesbianism, domestic violence, reproductive rights, journalism, literature, the arts, prostitution and women's rights. Types of materials include newsletters, pamphlets, flyers, catalogs, handbooks, brochures, syllabi, clippings, and bibliographies. There are some student papers and other manuscript material, but the collection consists primarily of printed materials. The collection is arranged alphabetically by subject.
The Collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Note: This collection has not been fully processed and may be somewhat difficult to use. This means the container list may not have very detailed descriptions, or be completely accurate. Some items may also be fragile or deteriorated, requiring further preservation treatment. Handle fragile or deteriorated items with extreme care. Locations of materials are subject to change when the collection is fully processed at a later date; therefore, when citing materials do not depend solely on box and folder numbers as they may change.
The UMASS-Amherst Women's Studies Department Collection was donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1987 by Karen Lederer. Subsequent donations have been filed in the Sophia Smith Collection's subject collections.
Abortion -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Family violence -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Lesbians -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Rape -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Reproductive health -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Women's rights -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Women's studies -- History; University of Massachusetts (Amherst campus). Dept. of Women's Studies
- SERIES I. SUBJECT FILES
  - Abortion: flyers, letters, proposals and conference programs and schedules (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Affirmative action: "Project on the Status and Education of Women" periodicals, lists and clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AIDS: single pamphlet, "What Every Student Should Know" 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Assoc. of University Women: single pamphlet, "AAUW Is..." n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anthropology: student papers, photocopied excerpts (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arts: reviews, clippings, ephemera, and "afterimage" issues (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Athletics: publications and material on sex discrimination (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Biology: Women in Cell Biology, 1976-78 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Business management: Newsletters, mailings, flyers and studies (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Childcare: writings, publications, newsletters (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chilean women: newsletter, "Action for Women In Chile" packet and guide (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Civil rights: "Catalogue of Publications," U.S. Commission on Civil Rights 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Contraception: clipping from '74, World Watch Paper 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Counseling psychology: Women's Institute of Alternative Psychology publications, clipping, presentation (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Curriculum material (non-sexist): syllabi, administrative materials (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dance: clippings (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Discrimination: memo (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Divorce: essay (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Domestic Violence: letter, newsletter, essay (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Encyclopedia of Women: chronology (Vol. 1) 1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - E.R.A: clippings, memos, NOW material (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Grand Jury: flyers, "people's guides," and clippings (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Health care: Reports, essays, newsletters (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Journalism: syllabus, Her Say newsletters (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - History: university program pamphlets, clippings, essays, etc. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Law: letters, publications, university program pamphlets, publications etc. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lesbian issues: newsletters, Lesbian Herstory Archive, literature (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Literature: newsletters, university programs (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Newsletters
    - Academy of Management (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Alert (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - American Friends Service Committee (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Chronicle (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Council for Women in Massachusetts for Higher Public Educatio n (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Conscience (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Echoes (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - EDC News (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - ETS Developments (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Livelihoods (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Isis (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Matrices (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Monitor (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous titles (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
    - Peer Perspective (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - SANEnews (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Sociologists for Women in Society (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Tabs (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Task Force Report/ It's Time (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - William Petscheck National Jewish Family Center (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - WEECN (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - UWW Newsletter (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Voice for Girls (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Older women: newsletters 1973-85, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Political Science: syllabus, periodical and speech 1971-76 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pornography: Feminist Anti-Pornography News: An Action Bulletin (Vol. I Number 1), 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Presidential Commission on the Status of Women: review with manuscript material 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Professional organizations: clippings, pamphlet, listings and periodical 1977-81, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Project on the Status of Women: newsletters and field reports 1975-84 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Prostitution: edited manuscripts/ essays, interview and publication 1975, n.d (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Rape: handbooks, reference material, clipping, and reviews 1975-87, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Religion: Clippings, bibliography, pamphlets, and newsletters 1976-84 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Record: publications, catalogs, advertisements, clippings, letters, supplements 1976-85 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Research resources: university pamphlets, brochures, newsletters and publications 1974-82 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sexuality: periodicals, statements and advertisement 1973-83 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 622: periodical 1975, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Third world women: mailings, bibliography, publications, clippings 1975-81 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Title IX: "Project on the Status and Education of Women" publications, evaluation, letters, supplements 1975-83 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - WEAL [Women's Equity Action League]: WEAL fund kit, publications, newsletters 1979-82 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Women from other cultures: Advertisements, newsletter, pamphlets 1974-19 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Women's History Research Center: press releases/letters from Center, course listing, advertisement, 19776-82, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Women writers: clippings, newsletters, pamphlets, bibliographies, reading lists, syllabi 1972-84 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Women and work: various periodicals 1982, 1985, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Women's Studies Quarterly: letter/press release, and Forum 1982-83 (Box 3, Folder 22)